Speaker 1: Hey all, Peter Zion here coming from Colorado. Today we're going to dive into our open-ended
Speaker 1: series on the impacts of the Iran war and everybody else. We've talked about the United
Speaker 1: States at length and the Persian Gulf countries of course, but what about everyone else?
Speaker 1: The region used to export 22 million barrels of crew today. It is now down to probably something
Speaker 1: between 10 and 12. So we're already looking at a shortage of 400 to 450 million barrels that
Speaker 1: haven't gotten out. And a lot of that shut-in is going to remain shut-in for, assuming no additional
Speaker 1: damage, it'll remain shut-in for a minimum of another nine months after the guns stop firing.
Speaker 1: And in the case of some of the Iraqi production, probably well over two years. These aren't shale
Speaker 1: wells where you can just turn them on and off. Anyway, that has a lot of impacts on a lot of
Speaker 1: people. We are only in the preliminary days of seeing oil prices go up. It was only last week
Speaker 1: that the last of the oil tankers pre-war from the Persian Gulf made it to Northeast Asia, and it'll be
Speaker 1: this week that the last make it to Western Europe. So what was a failure in throughput is now becoming
Speaker 1: a failure in supply. And we're going to see that impact all kinds of things. So let's start with
Speaker 1: the former Soviet Union, specifically Russia and Ukraine. In the opening days of the war, the
Speaker 1: conventional wisdom was twofold. Number one, there's no way that Ukraine comes out of this in a better
Speaker 1: position. The Western world, the whole world, is going to be distracted by what's going on in the
Speaker 1: Persian Gulf, which for most countries is more significant than what happens in the Russian near
Speaker 1: abroad. The United States is going to be diverting its weapons system, most notably its missile
Speaker 1: interceptors, to its own needs in theater rather than sending them to Ukraine. And on the flip side,
Speaker 1: Russia's going to make mad bank. Oil prices had been moderate until the war started. Now they're
Speaker 1: regularly over $100 a barrel. And if you consider that the break-even cost for a lot of Russian fields
Speaker 1: are between $30 and $50 a barrel, and they went from selling at $60 to $100, you know, you've seen
Speaker 1: the profit for Russian oil sales increase by a factor of $5 or more almost overnight. And that cash
Speaker 1: coming in is obviously going to remake what Russia can do with the war. Most of their equipment comes
Speaker 1: from China, but the China insists on hard currency payments, and that requires oil sales. That was the
Speaker 1: conventional wisdom, and there's nothing wrong with that. But now that we're five weeks in, we're seeing a
Speaker 1: much more nuanced picture with a lot of unexpected upsides and downsides for both sides. Let's start
Speaker 1: with the Russians. The Russians have been actively providing intelligence and techniques and hardware
Speaker 1: to the Iranian government to target the United States forces in region. While Donald Trump remains
Speaker 1: firmly in Putin's pocket, that is drastically adjusting things in the Defense Department and on Capitol
Speaker 1: Hill Hill, where we're seeing significant unrest in the United States with Donald Trump's policies in a way
Speaker 1: that can't help the Russians long term. More importantly, the Russians and the Iranians are not the only ones
Speaker 1: with drones. And during the war, the Ukrainians have showcased a new set of hardware with a little bit
Speaker 1: longer range and have used it to completely destroy the export capacity of Russian oil exports from the Baltic Sea.
Speaker 1: It's conservatively removing a million and a half
Speaker 1: barrels a day of exports, maybe up to two million, because the Russians can't really redirect. They don't have a backup pipeline system. And so what
Speaker 1: was originally this big windfall has turned into a structural loss for them in terms of oil exports. They're still earning more money overall, but once the Ukrainians are done with the St. Petersburg region,
Speaker 1: they're just going to turn those drones under the next oil producing and transiting system. And we may not have any meaningful Russian exports from either the Baltic or the Black Sea within three months. We're that close.
Speaker 1: Second, Ukraine itself. The year that the Ukrainians have had to basically operate without American assistance, they've used to great effect in innovating into the drone space, specifically in counter drone technology. They've got something called the Brave One, which can fit into a duffel bag and has limited range, not a great success rate, maybe 50%, but it only costs $2,000 to $3,000 to make versus $30,000 to $50,000
Speaker 1: for a Shahed versus $4,000 for a Pac-3. So Zelensky in the last couple of weeks has been all over the Persian Gulf signing deals specifically with Kuwait and Qatar and the United Arab Emirates and Saudi Arabia, each multi-billion dollar deals to invest in drone production.
Speaker 1: The Ukrainian problem this last year hasn't been innovation. It's having the cash necessary to buy all the materials to make it. Probably half of the industrial plant that they've expanded in Ukraine
Speaker 1: in the last year is not being used because they don't have the money. Well, say what you will about the Gulf arms, money is not the limiting factor.
Speaker 1: So we're going to be seeing money pouring into these facilities in Ukraine, which is going to drastically increase the defense of Ukraine from the Russians.
Speaker 1: At the same time, they'll be exporting drones to the Gulf states and the Gulf states will be building their own counter drone factories.
Speaker 1: So we're talking about a whole number of countries that five years ago, no one really considered to be at the forefront of military tech.
Speaker 1: All of a sudden, at the forefront of military tech in a way that the United States can't participate in and isn't benefiting from.
Speaker 1: So we've seen Ukraine and Russia get weird ups and downs in ways that were completely unexpected just a few weeks ago.
Speaker 1: But perhaps the biggest impact of this is because the Russians are so actively assisting the Iranians,
Speaker 1: is that all of the Arabs of the Persian Gulf are noodling over what's next for them vis-a-vis the Russians and the United States.
Speaker 1: And if you remember back to roughly 1985, when Reagan really started pushing hard on the Soviet Union,
Speaker 1: that was the year that the Saudis decided to drastically open up oil production in order to flood the market and bankrupt what was then the Soviet Union.
Speaker 1: We now have the beginnings of a second generation of some sort of alliance like that.
Speaker 1: But instead of the United States, it's the Europeans.
Speaker 1: Instead of NATO, it's Ukraine.
Speaker 1: And so we've got a number of pieces moving here, building new geopolitical alignments that really look very, very bad long term for Russia.
Speaker 1: None of this I probably would have guessed at two months ago, but here we are.